Patrick F. Leahy, Jr.

2722 Jacqueline Drive Apt. M-24 North Wilmington, DE 19810

(Mobile): (484) 574-0096 (E-mail): pleahyjr@hotmail.com

SUMMARY:

Genuine, enthusiastic, compassionate, flexible, well-rounded, professional educator seeks the opportunity to share a commitment to the social and academic development of students. Offering life experiences in school and team settings based on relationship building, problem solving, and integrity. Has the versatility to meet children's learning styles and abilities while fostering meaningful relationships with students, staff, and parents.

CERTIFICATIONS:

05/2011 Pennsylvania Instructional I Elementary Certification (K-6)

04/2012 Middle School Social Studies Certification (7-9) and Middle School Science Certification (7-9)

EDUCATION:

05/2011 **WEST CHESTER UNIVERSITY** - West Chester, Pennsylvania

Post-Baccalaureate Certification Program for Elementary Education (K-6)

- Cumulative Graduate **GPA 3.973**/4.0
- **Pi Lambda Theta Honor Society** (May 2011) Nominated for membership by The School of Education at West Chester University.

05/1994

LOYOLA UNIVERSITY - Baltimore, Maryland

Bachelor of Arts Degree in Psychology

• Cumulative GPA - 3.0/4.0

TECHNOLOGY SKILLS: SMARTboard Workshop Certificate - West Chester University College of Education Technology Center (11/2010), Promethean board and Document Camera (Spring 2011), MAC (*PowerSchool/S.A.M.*{Student Access Manager} = Attendance & Gradebook), PC, and Internet (Google Docs, First in Math, Study Island) (Spring 2013), iPad (2014-15).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE:

11/2014 - Present

BETHEL SPRINGS ELEMENTARY SCHOOL – DAILY BUILDING SUBSTITUTE, Grades 1-5 – Garnet Valley School District – Pennsylvania

- Experienced in Fundations K-3 Phonics Program, Pearson's Interactive Math Program, and Writer's Workshop.
- Maximized use of e-resources such as class iPads and educational applications to compliment standards based lesson plans. (iBooks, iTooch, Raz Kids).
- Administered DIBELS (Dynamic Indicators of Basic Early Literacy Skills) & PSSA's.
- Exercised flexibility to accommodate daily changing schedules and various administrative tasks.
- Utilized free time to prepare, research, and/or create additions to teachers' plans to enhance the students' learning experience.

10/2013 - 06/2014

PENN'S GROVE MIDDLE SCHOOL – LONG TERM SUBSTITUTE, Grades 8 & 7, Science – Oxford Area School District – Pennsylvania.

<u>Grade 8</u> (10/2013 – 4/2014): Chemistry / Physics (Force, Motion, Newton's Laws, Energy) / Sound & Light (waves) (Scientific Exploration)

- Prepared lessons independently based on Pennsylvania State Standards for science.
- Adapted classroom instruction and assessments for diverse population across five multi-cultural classes with varying degrees of achievement, including needs outlined in IEP's & 504's.
- Encouraged critical thinking skills through student centered lessons and activities containing stimulating discussions and purposeful writing.
- Participated actively in team and staff meetings while maintaining administrative expectations.
- Proactive communication with parents regularly, as well as during parent-teacher conferences.

Patrick F. Leahy, Jr.-PAGE 2

Grade 7 (5/2014 – 6/2014): Genetics / Natural Selection / Classification

- Adapt classroom instruction by using visual aids and real world examples to optimize student achievement in their understanding of genetics.
- Implemented review activities at the beginning of class to immediately focus students and maximize use of each available teaching minute.
- Documented academic, social, and emotional performance through various assessments.
- Collaborative team and hands-on *Dissection of a Frog* lab.

01/2013 - 06/2013

CHARLES F. PATTON MIDDLE SCHOOL – LONG TERM SUBSTITUTE, Grade 6, Life Science and Core English – Unionville-Chadds Ford School District – Pennsylvania.

- Guided a diverse population of learners which included needs outlined in IST's, IEP's, & 504's.
- Developed and instructed standards-based lessons focusing on developing reading, writing, and listening skills across the science and English curriculums.
- Cultivated an inquiry based environment to foster critical thinking skills and to connect life science concepts with everyday life to engage and motivate students.
- Utilized many student-centered learning techniques including demonstrations, labs, projects, *science buddies* and *clock buddies* for cooperative learning experiences.
- Assessed student learning formally and informally using a variety of assessments and rubrics.
- Created a webpage informing students and parents of daily lessons, homework, & assessments.
- Established behavior expectations and procedures to minimize class management issues.
- Participated in additional school events such as the community fair, student- teacher basketball game, students' *teacher for a day*, and evening honors ceremony.
- Effectively planned team activities and integrated lessons with grade level teachers.
- Actively participated in 504, IEP, and IST meetings and parent conferences.
- Participated in *Differentiated Instruction* and *Grading Issues* induction seminars.

09/2011 - Present

SUBSTITUTE TEACHER SERVICE, INC. – SUBSTITUTE TEACHER, Grades K-8, CHESTER & DELAWARE COUNTY SCHOOL DISTRICTS – Pennsylvania.

- Consistently requested as a favorite substitute by educators teaching Science, Language Arts, Social Studies, and Math.
- Early arrival, review plans and environment, read and learn students' assignments, manage and guide the students, revise approaches as needed, and summarize in detail the day's events.
- Followed teacher's lesson plans in an organized and flexible approach to provide consistency for students' studies.

01/2011 - 05/2011

MARY C. HOWSE ELEMENTARY - STUDENT TEACHER, Grade 2, - West Chester, Pennsylvania.

- Implemented lesson plans in all subject areas with differentiated instruction for special education and gifted students and aligned them to meet state and national standards.
- Created "hands on mind on" lesson plans.
- Enhanced lessons with cooperative learning opportunities.
- Designed two, week long, interactive units (science and social studies) to engage 80 second graders (four separate classes) and adapted each unit to meet the needs of each class.
- Facilitated summative and formative assessments to ensure students meet benchmarks.
- Stimulated individual thinking, curiosity, and knowledge through guided discovery.
- Earned high marks for the quality and creativity of classroom teaching, lesson plans and instructional materials used in teaching diverse subjects (e.g., language arts Reader's Theater, Writer's Workshop, mathematics Investigations, science Animal Classification and Organisms, and social studies Landforms).

Patrick F. Leahy, Jr.-PAGE 3

RELATED EXPERIENCE:	
11/2010 - 12/2010	THE GARAGE COMMUNITY AND YOUTH CENTER - Kennett Square, Pennsylvania VOLUNTEER - Served as a positive role model for middle and high school aged children.
11/2010 - 12/2010	CASE STUDY IN LITERACY - Tutored a third grade ADHD student to improve reading comprehension through multiple reading strategies (semantic mapping to activate prior knowledge, 'stop and think' monitoring, 'read-aloud' routine {decoding}, KWL chart, and a running record).
10/2010	PENNSYVANIA MIDDLE SCHOOL ASSOCIATION - Shadow a Middle Level Student Opportunity Certificate - Unionville Middle School - 8th grade.
03/2010	OBSERVATIONS - Hillendale Elementary School - 35 hours - grades K-5.